Muhammad Aswan Syahputra

FOOD SENSORU CONSULTANT · SENSOMETRICS ANALYST

Bernhardstraat 23, 6707 CH, Wageningen, Netherlands

🛘 (+62) 822-3465-3816 | 🗷 aswansyahputra@sensolution.id | 🌴 https://aswansyahputra.com/ | 🖸 aswansyahputra | 🗖 aswansyahputra

"... how hard one finds it to learn something is a function of the intrinsic difficulty of the thing, the person's previous experience, preferred modes of thinking, etc., and how learning is approached." - John Fox

Summary_

MSc graduate in Food Technology at Wageningen University and Research with Sensory Science specialisation. Independent data analyst and statistic consultant for bachelor and master student. Numerous experience in analysing statistical problems including process optimisation in food production. 3+ years experience working with R statistical program. Interested in Sensometrics and Data Science by utilising the power of open-source tools.

Education

Wageningen University and Research

MASTER IN FOOD TECHNOLOGY

• Granted with Indonesian Education Scholarship from Indonesia Endowment Fund of Education.

Universitas Brawijaya

BACHELOR IN AGRICULTURAL PRODUCT TECHNOLOGY

• Granted with PPA Scholarship from Ministry of Research, Technology and Higher Education of Indonesia.

Wageningen, Netherlands

Aug. 2016 - Aug. 2018

Malang, Indonesia

Sep. 2011 - Aug. 2015

Research Experience

SenseHub: an integrated web application for sensory analyses

PRESENTATION AT INTERNATIONAL COFERENCE ON GREEN AGROINDUSTRY AND BIOECONOMIC (ICGAB)

Malang, Indonesia

Sep. 2018

Observation of Chewing Activity using Photoplethysmography (PPG) Method

MASTER THESIS

Wageningen University and Research, Netherlands

Apr. 2018

Exploratory Study: the Influence of Instant Iced-Coffee Drinking Methods to Consumers' Multisensory Perceptions Utilizing Rate-all-that-Apply (RATA) Method

BACHELOR THESIS

University of Brawijaya, Indonesia

2015

Influence of Tempeh Flour Fortification into Coffee as an Anti-Hypercholesterolemia and Anti-Hypertension Beverages

STUDENT RESEARCH PROJECT

University of Brawijaya, Indonesia

2014

Uplift Indigenous "Rujak Manis" Potency to Lower Colorectal Cancer Incidence Through Osmotic Dehydration Technology

STUDENT RESEARCH PROJECT

University of Brawijaya, Indonesia

2013

Work Experience_

Association of Indonesian Education Scholarship Awardee in Wageningen University and Research

Wageningen, Netherlands

2016 - PRESENT

COORDINATOR

- Act as the mediator between awardee and Indonesia Endowment Fund of Education as scholarship granting organisation.
- Give academical insight and welcoming lecture to the new awardee in the beginning of new academic year.
- · Monitor academic and living performance of awardee and provide private/group consultation if necessary.

Laboratory of Sensory Analysis, Faculty of Agricultural Technology, University of Brawiiava

Malang, Indonesia

LABORATORY PRACTICE ASSISTANT 2015

- · Responsible in preparing the practical about discriminative, descriptive, and affective sensory test.
- Assisting students and making sure of the safety during laboratory practice.
- · Evaluating students performance and giving report to course coordinator about the laboratory practice.

Indonesian Coffee and Cocoa Research Institute (ICCRI)

Jember, Indonesia

2013 - 2014

INTERN Assisting sensory evaluation using Coffee Cupping Protocols established by Specialty Coffee Association of America (SCAA).

• Assisting sensory evaluation of cocoa products developed at ICCRI.

Laboratory of Post-harvest Processing Technology, Faculty of Agricultural Technology, **University of Brawijaya**

Malang, Indonesia

LABORATORY PRACTICE ASSISTANT

2013

- Responsible in preparing materials and protocol for the practical.
- Assisting students and making sure of the safety during laboratory practice.
- · Evaluating students performance and giving report to course coordinator about the laboratory practice.

HIMALOGISTA (Student Association)

Malang, Indonesia

2012 - 2014

· Delivering extra lectures for students on subject covering Food Physical-Chemical Properties, Food Processing Technology, and Basic Instrumental Analysis.

Laboratory of Chemistry, Faculty of Agricultural Technology, University of Brawijaya

Malana. Indonesia

LABORATORY PRACTICE ASSISTANT

- Responsible in preparing materials and protocol for the practical.
- Assisting students and making sure of the safety during laboratory practice.
- · Evaluating students performance and giving report to course coordinator about the laboratory practice.

Extracurricular Activity_

2017 Head of Rehearsal Division , Angklung Wageningen, Indonesian Student Association of Wageningen (ISAW)	Netherlands
2015 - Member, Food Sensory Research Group, University of Brawijaya	Indonesia
t	doco.d
2013 - 2014 Member , Riset dan Karya Ilmiah Mahasiswa (RKIM), University of Brawijaya	Indonesia
2012 - 2013 Member , Perhimpunan Ahli Teknologi Pangan Indonesia	Indonesia
2011 - 2012 Member , Ikatan Mahasiswa Muslim Peduli Pangan dan Gizi (IMMPPG), University of Brawijaya	Indonesia

Program Committees _____

2013	Organiser, ASTRA 1st University of Brawijaya Presentation and Seminar Workshop	Malang, Indonesia
2012	Organiser, 3rd Scientific Great Moment (SGM) University of Brawijaya	Malang, Indonesia

Honors & Awards

2017	2nd Winner, Traditional Saman Dance Competition, Indonesian Festival "Spirit of Youth"	Germany
2015	Cum laude Graduate, University of Brawijaya Graduation Ceremony	Indonesia
2014	1st Winner , 5th Scientific Great Momen (SGM) University of Brawijaya National Scientific Paper Competition	Indonesia
2013	2nd Winner, 11th Bogor Agricultural University National Scientific Paper Competition	Indonesia
2012	1st Winner, The Favorite Student in Faculty of Agricultural Technology	Indonesia
2011	1st Winner, Achiever of Best CGPA in Exact Science in University of Brawijaya	Indonesia

Ski**lls**

Computer and programming Linux, R, SPSS, Minitab, Jamovi, Design Expert, LaTeX Sensory software and package EyeQuestion, SensoMineR, FactoMineR, sensR, BradleyTerry2

> Graphic Inkscape, GIMP

Languages Bahasa Indonesia, English

Certification

Introduction to R R Programmer course track	DataCamp 2017
Intermediate R R Programmer course track	DataCamp 2017
Intermediate R - Practice R Programmer course track	DataCamp 2017
Importing Data Into R (Part 1) R Programmer course track	DataCamp 2017
Writing Efficient R Code R Programmer course track	DataCamp 2017
Cleaning Data in R R Programmer course track	DataCamp 2017
Working with the RStudio IDE (Part 1) R Programmer course track	DataCamp 2017
Modeling with Data in the Tidyverse Tidyverse Fundamentals with R course track	DataCamp 2018
Building Web Application in R with Shiny R Programmer course track	DataCamp 2018
Building Web Application in R with Shiny: Case Studies R Programmer course track	DataCamp 2018